{"tossups": [{"question": "This city\u2019s CRASH anti-gang unit was the subject of the Rampart police corruption scandal in the late-1990s. Sixteen people died in this city\u2019s Northridge Meadows Apartments on Reseda Boulevard in a 1994 earthquake.<em> Rebel Without a Cause</em> was set in this city, filming at its Griffith Observatory. Sid Grauman built a \u201cChinese Theater\u201d and an \u201cEgyptian Theater\u201d in this city. Brentwood and Bel-Air are neighborhoods of, for the point, what most populous city of California?", "answer": "<b> Los Angeles</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man led a squadron of ships past a blockade of Presque Isle Bay to sail to Put-in-Bay. In one battle, this man transferred his command from the<em> Lawrence</em> to the<em> Niagara</em> when his first flagship was destroyed. After defeating a British fleet in an engagement during the War of 1812, this man declared\u201cWe have met the enemy and they are ours.\u201d For the point, name this victor of the Battle of Lake Erie.", "answer": "<b> O</b>liver Hazard<b> Perry</b> (prompt on Perry)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "3 million people near Chongqing. The Itaipu Dam was surpassed in power output after the completion of, for the point, what massive hydroelectric dam on the Yangtze River, the largest in the world?", "answer": "<b> Three Gorges</b> Dam", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The provisions of this document were reaffirmed by the<em> Resolutions</em> of Edward Coke. The standard edition of this document was compiled in the 18th Century by William Blackstone. This document, which was signed by Robert Fitzwalter, failed in preventing the outbreak of the First Barons\u2019 War. For the point, name this 1215 document providing liberties to the English people that was signed at Runnymede by a group of nobles and King John.", "answer": "<b> Magna Carta</b> (or the<b> Great Charter</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In one work, two princes from this country beat their wives after they are humiliated for being afraid of a lion. In another epic poem, this modern country is home to Marsile, king of the Saracens, who schemes with Ganelon to ambush their enemy as they head home through Roncevaux Pass.<em> The Song of Roland</em> depicts Charlemagne\u2019s war in, for the point, what modern European country where the Moors also fought against El Cid [el seed]?", "answer": "<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "In this state, George Pullman founded the model company town of Pullman; an 1894 strike began in that town, after which Governor John Peter Altgeld controversially opposed the presence of federal troops in this state. In 1887, Albert Parsons was one of four labor leaders to be executed in this state for their role in inciting a riot in which a bomb was thrown at a group of police officers. For the point, name this state where the Haymarket Affair rocked the city of Chicago.", "answer": "<b> Illinois</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A subset of this political party based in Essex County advocated secession from the United States. Charles Pinckney lost two Presidential elections as this party\u2019s candidate, and it faded after the Hartford Convention. This party was the opposition for the end of the First Party System, and only elected one President, John Adams. For the point, name this early American political party, supported by Alexander Hamilton, that opposed the Democratic-Republicans.", "answer": "<b> Federalist</b> Party (prompt on the Essex Junto)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One man with this occupation may have been opposed by a man named Heinz Thorvald or Erwin Konig, though historians cannot verify the story. Another person with this occupation lost his left cheek, served in the Winter War, and was called \u201cthe White Death.\u201d Vasily Zaytsev and Simo Hayha served in this role, as did the \u201cDevil of Ramadi,\u201d whose memoirs inspired a 2014 Clint Eastwood film. Chris Kyle served as, for the point, what type of military sharpshooter?", "answer": "<b> sniper</b>s (or<b> sharpshooter</b> before mentioned; prompt on soldier or other terms)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man marooned the ship captain Juan de Cartagena after a mutiny broke out aboard the<em> San</em> <em>Antonio</em>,<em> Victoria</em>, and<em> Concepcion</em>. This man, who gave the Pacific Ocean its name, was succeeded by Juan Elcano after he died at Mactan in a battle against the Lapu Lapu people. For the point, name this Portuguese explorer who died in the Philippines before his ships became the first to circumnavigate the globe.", "answer": "Ferdinand<b> Magellan</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of these instruments, supposedly the oldest still in existence, was part of a set of 38 made for King Charles IX of France. Giuseppe Tartini wrote a G minor sonata for it nicknamed \u201cDevil\u2019s Trill.\u201dDuring the Baroque era, this instrument was made by luthiers in Cremona such as Amati and Guarneri. A virtuoso who was rumored to have sold his soul to the devil, Niccolo Paganini, played, for the point, what high-pitched string instrument made by Antoni Stradivari?", "answer": "<b> violin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "While in exile, this man committed suicide in Bithynia after serving as an admiral for the Seleucid Empire. Fabius Maximus strategized that avoiding fighting this man in open battle would wear down his forces; after that policy was abandoned, this man enveloped a huge army at the Battle of Cannae. This general was finally defeated at the Battle of Zama by Scipio Africanus. For the point, name this Carthaginian general who brought elephants across the Alps to attack his nemesis, Rome.", "answer": "<b> Hannibal</b> Barca", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this film, George goes blind and eventually dies after being struck by a soldier found resting on a U-boat. On a train ride at the end of this film, Adam asks a character to read a newspaper that contains the recently delivered \u201cWe shall fight to the beaches\u201d speech. In this film, members of the RAF try to help with the central effort, in which \u201clittle ships\u201d end up saving over 300,000 troops. For the point, name this 2017 film about a massive 1940 evacuation from France in World War II.", "answer": "<b> Dunkirk</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "For the point, name this successor of Thomas Jefferson who led the US during the War of 1812 as the fourth President.", "answer": "James<b> Madison</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A kingdom of these people became fractured thanks to infighting between Dingane [din-gah-nay] and Mpande [im\u2019pahn-day] when they failed to check the advance of the voortrekkers. These people organized their military into groups called impis and used the buffalo horn formation to great effect at Isandlwana against European troops; however, their capital of Ulundi was eventually burned down in a war with the British. For the point, name this South African empire that was once led by Shaka.", "answer": "ama<b>Zulu</b> empire (or ama<b>Zulu</b> people, etc.; accept<b> Zulu</b>land) Page 3", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man began his country\u2019s trade with England after allowing Richard Chancellor to create the Muscovy Company. This man\u2019s rule was supported by the<em> oprichniki</em> secret police, which helped this man purge dissident nobles. The Time of Troubles began after this man\u2019s incapable son Feodor died; this man had accidentally killed his original heir in a rage. For the point, name this final Rurik tsar of Russia whose epithet highlights his cruelty.", "answer": "<b> Ivan the Terrible</b> (or<b> Ivan IV</b> Vasilyevich; accept<b> Ivan Grozny</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Blatnik Committee investigated corruption in this project, which was inspired by the Pershing Map. Diesel taxes were a primary method of financing this project, which one president intended partly to ensure fast domestic troop transport. That president, who was inspired to undertake this project after seeing the Autobahn in Germany, was Dwight Eisenhower. For the point, name this national infrastructure project that, today, includes nearly 50,000 miles of high speed roadway.", "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower National System of<b> Interstate</b> and Defense Highways (accept descriptive answers that use the term<b> Interstate</b>; prompt on other descriptive answers relating to highways)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Hundreds of thousands of residents of this state were expelled from their homes during the Nakba. Limited self-government for this state was established by the Oslo Accords in 1993. This state has been led by two presidents, Yasser Arafat and Mahmoud Abbas, and was given observer status in the UN in 2012. Over 100 countries - not including the United States - diplomatically recognize, for the point, what Middle Eastern state whose territory is disputed with Israel?", "answer": "State of<b> Palestine</b> Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This region accidentally became a refuge for the endangered Amur Leopard. After Arthur Bonifas and Mark Barrett were killed in an axe murder in this region, Operation Paul Bunyan was initiated to remove trees near the Bridge of No Return. This region was established after a military stalemate prompted the 1953 Armistice between Syngman Rhee and Kim Il-sung. For the point, name this strip located near the 38th parallel that separates North and South Korea.", "answer": "Korean<b> Demilitarized Zone</b> (or the Korean<b> DMZ</b>; prompt on Korea before said; prompt on 38th parallel before said; prompt on border between North and South Korea before \u201cseparates\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Edward R. Murrow said this man repeatedly crossed the line between investigation and persecution in an episode of<em> See It Now</em>. This man and Roy Cohn caused the firings of many gay government employees in the Lavender Scare. At a series of hearings investigating the Army, Senator Joseph Welch asked this man \u201cHave you no sense of decency?\u201d For the point, name this Wisconsin Senator who claimed 205 State Department officials were communists at the peak of the 1950s Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph<b> McCarthy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This empire\u2019s forces were decimated at the Battle of Khalkhin Gol by Georgy Zhukov. This country\u2019s Unit 731 experimented on people during a war begun by a battle at the Marco Polo Bridge. Six years earlier, this country staged an explosion near Mukden to invade and create the puppet state Manchukuo. The 1945 Jewel Voice radio broadcast announced the surrender of, for the point, what country after its cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki were bombed in World War II?", "answer": "Empire of<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader and Nicholas II exchanged a friendly series of telegrams mere weeks before the outbreak of World War I. During the Boxer Rebellion, this leader gave the \u201cHun Speech,\u201d which would later become a derogatory term for his own soldiers. This cousin of George V and Nicholas II allied with Austria-Hungary to form the Central Powers. For the point, name this last German Kaiser, who reigned during World War I.", "answer": "Kaiser<b> Wilhelm II</b> (or<b> William II</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This event\u2019s name was coined on an infamous April Sunday after 20 black blizzards formed at once. While fleeing from this event, Florence Owens Thompson was photographed by Dorothea Lange in a print titled<em> Migrant Mother</em>. Cattle overgrazing and the belief that \u201crain follows the plow\u201d were catalysts for this event. Many \u201cOkies\u201d went to California to escape, for the point, what Depression-era ecological disaster that ruined agriculture in the Great Plains?", "answer": "<b> Dust Bowl</b> (do not accept or prompt on Great Depression) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A workers strike in this country\u2019s city of Poznan led to the ascension of the moderate Wladyslaw Gomulka [vady-slav go-mul-ka]. In this country, the Interfactory Strike Committee issued 21 demands that led to the Gdansk Agreement. This country\u2019s government was reformed after the Round Table Agreement, which included the trade union Solidarity. Pope John Paul II called for a peaceful revolution in this country, his homeland. For the point, name this Eastern European country that Lech Walesa [vah-wen-sah] led from Warsaw.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Poland</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}